welcome back
this is Alec 5 4 4 2 and we're on unit 1
we're now looking at the third short video
to help you read through my notes limitations of DSP
now just in case you've looked at the other two videos
and think wow
it's going very fast
these videos are simply short byte sized 10 to 15
minute videos
to help you to go through the PDS
and they're simply to highlight some important points
and just to give you an overview
of what each section is about
so don't worry if you think they're going a little bit
too fast
they'll simply help you with your own self study
and that's the important thing
you have to do your own self study
these are not traditional
so there's the
generic setup with the five boxes the low pass
filter and the elasing filter
X of C continuous time signal into the analog
the digital converter
DSP chip the digital to 1 low converter
and the low past smoothing filter
will come on to this
so the
the errors that you can have inside a DSP
system are non ideal behavior
of the anti elysium Lupas filter so
this should cut off say exactly at
for example 4khz or 8khz or 10khz
but no filter will be exactly correct it
will not have a brick wall effect
transfer function like this
it'll have some ripples and it'll have a transition
band so that's because of the non ideal behavior of the
anti lec filter
some signal
energy will get through above the cutoff frequency
so you'll get aliasing errors at the a to d converter
very small depending on how good this filter is
you get quantization error here so you don't
when you sample the signal you don't actually
represent the signal samples exactly
you have to quantize them up as we've seen
you get to find out word effects
now what that means is that inside the DSP chip
say for example
using fixed point arithmetic
so every number was represented by it bits
that means where you get a multiplication for example
a 0 times x of n
that's going to be it bits that's going to be it bits
if you multiply two 8 bit numbers together you get 16
bits
and then you have to
round that down
to 8 bit so you get product rounding issues
so that will give you an error
when you add together
the individual terms a 0 x of n plus
a 1 x of n minus 1
so you're adding together to 8 bit numbers
you can get a 9 bit number
so you can get overflow that's outer overflow
adder overflow
in addition when you represent these coefficients
they're not represented
say for example you were designing a
very specific bound stop filter
and a 0 was minus 1.679432
you have to represent that
decimal number into 8 bits and so you'll get
coefficient
rounding or coefficient
quantization so coefficient quantization
multiplication product rind off rounding and
addition overflow
so there are some of the examples of the
finite word length effects
you get something else we're going to come onto called
multiply accumulate time restrictions of a DSP chip
I've put this in red because I'm going to come on
and cover this
and you get what's called the sync X distortion
of the Digital Tomato Loc converter
finally you get non ideal behavior of the
smoothing low pass filter
so just like the anti aliasing filter was not an
exact low pass filter
similarly for the smoothing filter
should point out
with all these errors DSP is still better than analog
so the only restriction
in using DSP is really the sampling rate
and that's gone up from you know
killer Hertz in the early days
to no gigahertz
so there really is very little restriction
but as carrier frequencies go further and further up
than the adidi converter
hasty try to match that
so what are multiply accumulate time restrictions so
here's the example of how we we are together
now the reason we call multiply accumulate
first of all let's explain that
we have to take say a 0 x of n plus a 1
x of n minus one plus a 2 x of n minus 2
what we're doing is we're taking a number of
products and we're adding them together
that is we're accumulating them
so if you look here that's addition
that's multiplication
and so here's the most common operation in DSP
it's multiply and accumulate so B time C+D becomes a
and you store a away and then you get F times G
and you add that to a
you accumulate that with a to get E
so multiply accumulate is
a really important function in a DSP ship chip
as is shifting
and that's why DSP chips have a
certain architecture that's different than normal
microprocessors
to deal with us
so we call and multiply accumulator mic operation
we look at we have optimized that in a DSP chip
so say for example
it might take 70 clock cycles with ordinary processors
it would be reduced onto one clock cycle with a DSP
chip
so that's what multiply accumulate as a multiply an art
so Mac I'm going to use that word multiply accumulate
down here multiply art and accumulate
okay so let's take a question
so let's assume a DSP chip is like this
we want to and the DSP chip is able to perform 100
million multiply cumula operations per second
calculate the maximum bandwidth
XC of t where XC of t is up here
so you can't remember a formula for this
you've just got to
write down the information and try to see
how you come up with the answer
so let's look at the problem
here we have the signal and sampled XC of t
continuous time signal
and what we have to do is
when we're working looking at the outputs I'd say
time n minus 1
and
looking at trying to calculate the output at time n
so we'll have the input x of n x of n minus 1
x P m minus 2
between that
we need to perform 20 multiply accumulates
so 20 multiply accumulates must be performed between
any one sampling period
otherwise we won't have calculated the
next output by the time the new input arrives
so using that principle there you can then say you need
um you can work out what the time is
for one multiply accumulate
and you need 20 of those must be less than equal to t
don't forget what the anoina is the Anoina's F of s
and once you find
f of
s then you know the bandwidth is going to be half of
s over 2 so that's really all there is to it
you don't have to remember that you just have to
understand what what the restriction is
so in this particular case
remind yourself there's 20 multiply accumulates
look k equals 0 to 19
a zero times x ban a 1 x ban minus 1 etc
and you can consider yourself the trade offs that might
exist in terms of if you can't manage to satisfy this
what do you do
well you could reduce the order of the filter but that
means your filter would behave worse
you could get a faster DSP chip etc etc
so what's the other limitation this Sync X equivalent
transfer function bdiwa converter
so let's look at the output here
from the d to a converter
so that's what the output y CFT will look like
from a 0 order hole d to a converter
and you can see why you need the
smoothing loop pass filter
to take out the high frequency content that's present
in those little
steps
now
one of the problems we have is
what's the equivalent transfer function for a data way
converter that might seem like a strange question but
think about it
you've got
discrete time in and you've got continuous time out
so
it's rather difficult to think of a
transfer function normally a transfer function
in the analog time domain as equal to the
Fury transform of the impulse response
and then the discrete time domain
you'll see later on it's equal to the dtft
of the impulse response
but here we've got
discrete time input continuous time output
so let's see what we can do with that
we're not being mathematically very rigorous
but we get the right answer
take me too long to
explain it in a more rigorous mathematical way
so there's a delta function
for discrete time
that's the impulse we put in
and that's the impulse response that we get coming out
so there's the impulse response
and we know that the
transfer functions equal to free
transform of the impulse response
that's from undergraduate lectures in
analog signal proceing or free transforms
so there's the fur E transform
if you take the fur E transform of H of t
make sure you can do it it's not difficult
you end up getting this expression here
and don't forget what sync is
sync X is sine X over X
so sine that over that gives you the sync function
so that's what the transfer function looks like
and if you plot that
function let's see what it looks like
so once it goes through the smoothing filter
we get back the original
say if you had a sine wave going in
you get a sine wave coming up
so what we can say is that in the frequency demand
here we have the furry transform of the output
equals the transfer function of the system
which was that sync function
times the furry transform of the input
and the furry transform of the input
is not a traditional furry transform
it's what's called the DTFT
discreet Timefurry transform will come to that later
I've explained that here
but that's the normal relationship between
output equals transfer function times input
where that's the very transform of YM
so there is the spectrum of y of N
that's the signal going into the dataway converter
we know that the spectrum repeats itself
every FS FS is the sampling frequency
now if you take that sync function
and be careful it's not totally obvious
plot it then it looks like this
so what do you get
coming out for the Freerier transform of y C
C meaning continuous time of t
will be the product of
H of F modulus H of F times modulus y in blue
so it's the red one multiplied with the blue
now you can see two problems that you get from the
sync function
the sync function is letting through
this part of the first repeated part of the spectrum
this part of the second
repeated part of the spectrum
so some of the high frequencies being picked up
and that's due to the strip lines
the other thing that happens is that
withinside the passbound
of
the
this bit here
which is what you really want to recover
because that's the furrier transform
of the analog signal that's what you want to recover
it's not flat
and so you get same X over X distortion
inside the pass band
so you get two things happening here
you get distortion inside the pass band
and you pick up some high frequency content
that's why we need the smoothing filter
so if you have an ideal smoothing filter
then what it does is it
gets rid of all that high frequency content
that you're picking up
by the Dataway Converter sine X over X
and what it also does
unfortunately does not do I should say
is this
distortion that you get with inside the pass band
one way rind that would be to have a
smoothing filter that goes like that
the inverse of the top of the sink
and they're quite difficult to design
so we don't normally do that
the way we do it is by up sampling after the
d to way after the DSP chip
so we increase the sampling frequency
and if you think if you stretch this out
then what will happen
this line it will come down shallower and shallower
and so it will
take in less and less high frequency components
but more
importantly as it becomes shallower and shallower
it becomes flutter and flutter
and so you reduce the cyan X over X distortion
so we don't have
our loopass filter which is the inverse
of the sync function
what we normally do is
we have what's called an up sampler here at yn
that is we increase the sampling frequency
so double it quadruplet whatever
and effectively if you increase f of s
and stretch that out
then you flatten this bit inside the passbound
and you can listen to this demo
which in my mudlog files which should help you
understand that
so that's two limitations of DSP
that I cover just to give you a feeling for them
so summary of the five DSP blocks
we should really say
what each block does and why it is needed
so I've done this for you and you can read through this
again be careful now I've
carefully chosen every single word
what each block does and why it is needed
they're two completely different things
so there's the five
and the first low pass filter
I'll just do this from what it does
it's a low pass down to the leasing filter
it moves all the signal energy
above half the sampling frequency
or sometimes even lower
if there's a guard bun
why
why do you do that
it's there to ensure that no
lacing occurs in the sample signal right
for this the sampling rate can be greater than an
equal to the niquis rate
so when the analog signal comes into the attid
converter you've no idea what Bondworth it is
by putting it through the low pass filter first
you know exactly what the Bondworth is
so if you read through these yourselves
what and why each block is used
we've come with that already
okay so I'll stop there and that's the end of video 3
I'll continue with video 4 for discrete time signals